Future is Female Project Records, 1979-1990
Sophia Smith Collection
Future is Female Project records
1979-1990
Future is Female Project
MS 463
15 boxes (18 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
A research project undertaken in the early 1980s by Annie Cheatham and Mary Clare Powell. They interviewed North American women about their efforts to create alternative structures for family life, arts, education, work, and politics. The results were published in the book, This Way Daybreak Comes: Women's Values and the Future (1986). Project records contain research material, writings, speeches, correspondence, slides, and photographs. Of particular interest are audio interviews of women in a variety of occupations and living situations throughout North America.
The Future Is Female Project was a research project undertaken by Annie Cheatham and Mary Clare Powell. In the early 1980s, Cheatham, who had worked as Director of the Congressional Clearinghouse on the Future, and Powell, an artist, interviewed North American women for information about their efforts to create alternative structures for family life, arts, education, work, and politics. The resulting book, This Way Daybreak Comes: Women's Values and the Future, was published in 1986.
Project records contain background research material, writings, speeches, correspondence, slides, and photographs pertaining to the Future Is Female Project and the writing of This Way Daybreak Comes. Of particular interest are audiotaped interviews of women in a variety of occupations and living situations throughout North America.
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection with the following caveats:
The collection is stored offsite; researchers must give 48 hours advance notice.
Access to audiovisual materials may first require production of research copies.
This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.
Feminism--North America--History--20th century--Sources; Women--History--20th century--Sources; Women artists--History--20th century--Sources; Women--North America--Interviews; Powell, Mary Clare. This Way Daybreak Comes: Women's Values and the Future (1986)--Sources; Cheatham, Annie. This Way Daybreak Comes: Women's Values and the Future (1986)--Sources
- This Way Daybreak Comes: manuscripts, drafts, notes, and correspondence 1984-85 (Box 1)
- Future Is Female: traveling interview project materials, correspondence, publicity, notes, printed materials, schedules, financial materials 1979-86 (Box 1)
- Research, printed material 1981-86 (Box 1)
- Book chapters/ Future Is Female interviews, publicity, research materials, audiotape, correspondence 1981-84 (Box 2-3)
- Research materials: printed material, clippings, publicity, brochures re: art chapter 1981-84 (Box 4-5)
- Research materials (Box 6)
- Book galleys 1990 (Box 6)
- Audiotaped interviews 1982-85 (Box 7)
- 4 card files of addresses undated (Box 8)
- Book cover art (Box 9)
- Feminist Futures International Network newsletters, drafts, mailing lists, [edited by Cheatham/Powell-Institute for Women and the Future] 1988 (Box 9)
- Correspondence, response to book 1983-88 (Box 9)
- Organization subject files re: proposed conference circa 1980 (Box 9)
- Subject files, research materials, correspondence 1979-88 (Box 9)
- Photos, correspondence, memorabilia 1985 (Box 10)
- Book mail 1985-87 (Box 10)
- Women's movement printed material, books of poetry, magazines, directories 1980-86 (Box 10)
- Scrapbook re: art exhibit 1981-82 (Box 11)
- Book drafts, notes, press materials, publishers correspondence 1984, undated (Box 12)
- Book royalties, press and publishers correspondence, reviews 1984-87 (Box 12)
- Conferences, proposed projects 1987 (Box 12)
- Speeches and presentations 1987 (Box 12)
- Great Britain trip 1986-88 (Box 13)
- European tour dead ends (Box 13)
- England speech (Box 13)
- 5 inch disks of Daybreak (Box 13)
- Slides of art and individuals 1982-86 (Box 13)
- Journals, logs, correspondence, and photos from trip 1982-85 (Box 13)
- Copies of handouts and explanatory materials for trip (Box 13)
- Daybreak, hard and soft cover (Box 13)
- Future is Female newsletter 1982 (Box 13)
- Schedules and mailing lists (Box 13)
- Trip narratives and slides circa 1982 (Box 14)